<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
<channel><!--  RSS generated by ecstatic, a minimal static site generator  --><title>Ronit Ray's Blog</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/</link>
<description>Feed for Ronit Ray's personal blog</description>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 2021-03-08</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<title>How I Handle My Passwords</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/passwords-private.html</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2021</pubDate>
<description>My only-slightly eccentric and perhaps unnecessary password workflow.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post comes in soon after <a href="https://blog.lastpass.com/2021/02/changes-to-lastpass-free/">LastPass announced</a> that they are restructuring their free tier to only allow access from one category of devices, i.e. only desktops or only mobile devices. I assume this will be a no-go for many users, and given the high (~$36/year) subscription costs, several people will be unwilling to upgrade to their premium offering.</p>

<p>If you're not using a password manager, you're just asking for trouble, and/or putting in a lot of unnecessary effort memorizing several passwords when you could just remember one. My recommendation to anyone who is starting out or looking to switch from LastPass and wants a very similar experience is the excellent <a href="https://bitwarden.com/">Bitwarden</a>, a free and open source offering that offers most of the features you would need in their free tier and also a few premium options at roughly $10 a year. It is far from the only option though, there are several very good recommendations a simple web search will get you.</p>

<h3>What Password Manager Do I Use?</h3>

<p>I've been meaning to document the slightly eccentric way I manage my passwords for a while, so here goes. My password manager of choice is <a href="https://keepassxc.org/"><strong>KeepassXC</strong></a>. What do I like about it?</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It is <strong>offline</strong>. You don't need to be connected to the internet to access your passwords or check secure notes.</p></li>
<li><p>Everything is on a <strong>single file</strong>. While an argument can be made that it is a single point of failure and if the file is corrupted you lose all your passwords, I haven't really experienced or encountered any such issues in the few years I've been following news on password managers. Having the entire database be a single file is great for portability purposes.</p></li>
<li><p>The option to use a <strong>keyfile</strong> alongside your password is great for security, and since any file can be a keyfile, it's a pretty good foil for someone who gains access to your computer by chance.</p></li>
<li><p>It is <strong>open-source</strong>, audited, and has been around for years. This is, for me, a good enough marker of trust. Further, it's not a SaaS product so even if development on one KeePass client stops tomorrow, I lose essentially nothing. I can continue using the present version of the client indefinitely, or switch to a new client without changing much because the underlying standard remains the same. </p></li>
</ul>

<h3>How Do I Store My Passwords?</h3>

<p>I have a keepass .kdbx database and a 128bit keyfile. These lie in an encrypted <a href="https://www.veracrypt.fr/en/Home.html">Veracrypt</a> container on my PC that is dismounted until I need it. </p>

<p>That would be the end of it if I only stuck to my PC, but I have a bad habit of using my phone for certain online accounts, and I also needed the security of having my passwords backed up in case my computer failed or was lost/stolen, or if I needed access to them in a pinch on some other device. Here's what I did to get around that.</p>

<p><strong>For mobile</strong>, I use <a href="https://syncthing.net/"><strong>Syncthing</strong></a>. The password database is synced over Syncthing every once in a while, either manually when I add or update a password, or periodically to be safe. The keyfile doesn't go over Syncthing, I had transferred it offline over USB. Probably unnecessary, but I did it anyway. The Android client I use is <a href="https://www.keepassdx.com/"><strong>KeePassDX</strong></a>, although <a href="https://github.com/PhilippC/keepass2android">KeePass2Android</a> is a very good option too. Both have essentially the same feature set and are open-source and reliable. They support Android's native autofill, but since this is hit and miss on my current phone (a major pain point when I used to use LastPass,and then Bitwarden), I've taken to using the <strong>virtual keyboard</strong> provided by both these apps. Essentially, when you want to login, you select the entry from your vault and load the virtual keyboard. It will then fill in whatever field you want from your vault without using the clipboard or any nasty shenanigans. Clipboard hijacking is among the easiest ways to grab someone's password, and it is a nightmare on Android since <a href="https://www.aol.com/video/view/5f024c3f3092ab5c5b6f0441/">a ton of applications have been caught snooping on clipboard contents indiscriminately in the past.</a></p>

<p><strong>Cloud</strong> backups have undeniable advantages, and the convenience factor for SaaS password vaults like LastPass, Dashlane etc is undeniable. Now, KeePass databases are encrypted using AES, so you should be good to go by just backing up said database over a cloud storage provider of your choice. Because I thrive on paranoia and I don't like making things easy for myself, I took this a step further and instead back up the veracrypt container rather than the database. This is presently done over Git but it can be replaced by pretty much any cloud storage provider. This way there are at least two layers of one of the most reliable encryption schemes we know that stand guard before my passwords. Of course, none of this matters if AES is broken in the near or distant future, but that is well outside my threat model at the moment.</p>

<p>All this takes a good while to set up at first, but once you're set, I've found that you can pretty much go about your life painlessly and without any issues. Whether you go as far as I have or further is entirely dependent upon your threat model, but at the very least I definitely recommend using a password manager for everyone, from yourself to your grandparents. I'd always say an open-source option is the way to go, but mainstream proprietary products that have been around for a while, are unlikely to suddenly disappear, and have been audited are certainly much better than using no password manager at all.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ecstatic v0.1 Release</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/ecstatic-v01-release.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021</pubDate>
<description>Formally 'releasing' my static site generator project.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I am formally releasing v0.1 of Ecstatic, a static site generator that I wrote in Python using the Jinja template engine.</p>

<p>This generator was initially intended only to generate this blog, but I think I've been able to make it generic enough to be extensible.</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://github.com/RonitRay/ecstatic/">Source on GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ronitray.neocities.org/posts/ecstatic-documentation.html">Documentation</a></li>
</ol>

<p><em>Please note that this is a point release and is still very much a minimal and raw project. I definitely recommend getting your hands dirty with it, but you should think twice before deploying it in a production environment where things move quickly and break fast.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Art and Expectation</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/art-expectation-taylorswift-lovestory-fearless.html</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021</pubDate>
<description>I ramble about Taylor Swift re-releasing 'Fearless' and 'Love Story'.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><small>CW: mentions of suicide and mental health later in the article.</small></p>

<p>Taylor Swift and I were both young when I first saw (and heard) her. I was 13, and she 21. Like many before me, my first exposure to her was her song "Love Story", part of her second studio album titled 'Fearless'. It didn't take a lot for me to be hooked; it was a really good song that spoke to my teen anxieties like few others. I had a raging crush and wasted no time in purchasing the audio CD for the entire album. </p>

<p>In the years since, I've been a fairly avid "Swiftie", indeed, that CD still lies on my shelf as one of the few pieces of physical media from my teens I still own. I must have played every album until "Red" tens of dozens of times and have many of her lyrics memorized better than more important things. I did drop out of the fandom for a while when she released "1989" and "Revolution", both albums that had a distinctly different vibe to her usual fare. They are admittedly important for her journey as a musician, but they were not, and continue to not quite be "my thing" in terms of genre. She did, however, bowl me over once again in the blink of an eye with "Folklore" and the subsequent "Evermore". It felt incredible to rediscover an artist I held so dear not so long ago, and to see how her songwriting has matured.</p>

<p>This is why I was excited, curious, and just a tad skeptical when, yesterday, she announced on Twitter that she would be re-releasing 'Fearless' later as a version more true to who she is now this year, with six tracks that didn't make the cut the first time around. She kicked this off by releasing what she calls "Taylor's Version" of Love Story earlier today. My heart pounding and my fancy headphones on, I tuned into Spotify to check it out. </p>

<p>Four minutes of anticipation, four minutes of disappointment. The song is, for all intents and purposes, basically the same as the original with a few minor tonal differences. Don't get me wrong, it's still a great song, but it rings different for me personally. This post is me thinking out loud to try and understand why this is the case, and wondering what I even expected to get out of it. For my fellow fans and those more ardent than I'll ever be, I'm not saying she shouldn't have released it or that she owes us (me) anything, really. I'm trying to articulate why I feel deeply unsettled listening to this song despite there being very few differences on the surface.</p>

<p>My personal experience with music is that the first time you discover a track playing on the radio or a streaming service of your choice is a very different experience. You almost never know the artist, and the music is all there is for you. You judge it on the way it sounds, on how it is written, how it makes you feel. Perhaps you like it. Every subsequent listen attaches new memories, new interpretations and new expectations. As you learn more about the artist and immerse yourself in their work, the way the song feels to you becomes something else entirely, more than a purely auditory experience.</p>

<p>When I first heard Fearless, I was fresh off getting my heart broken a first time, and riding the wave of hormones that is adolescence. When she recorded it around 2008, Taylor would have been a teen herself, and I felt like she "understood", that she went through a number of the same things I did and was able to express them better than I ever could. Every time I've listened to the album since, that purity, that clarity of thought, the innocence is what I'm taken back to. I'm not the same person that I was in 2010. I've seen more of life and of love than who I was back then, and I know Taylor has as well because we've been on that journey with her with every album she has released. She's not exactly an artist who creates "concept pieces", each several layers of abstraction from the real world. With her, you know her music is deeply personal, her way of processing or discussing the things she goes through in real life. So when I listen to Love Story now, while I'm taken back to a simpler, a better, more hopeful and innocent time, I'm also reminded of how far I've come since then and how the meaning of love and my expectations from it have evolved along the years. I guess I just expected her to be able to express this abstract notion the way she has expressed the myriad things I've felt over the years even when I haven't been able to do so myself.</p>

<p>If you're re-releasing a piece of music almost 15 years since you've made it, my expectation is that you'd talk about (or sing about, really) how far you've come since then, whether you see life differently or want to go back to seeing things as they were when you first released it. In essence,  I think I just expected something substantially different in this new version. Someone I adore and respect greatly, who also happens to be a fan of Taylor's, mentioned that she could be in love again and could be feeling the same way she did back then. I feel like that's a very charitable reading of the situation and the new song as it is doesn't really give me any reason to interpret it that way. Of course, it could be possible. No one knows how an artist feels better than them, and what they choose to put out and how is entirely their choice. I just feel like it could have been really interesting if she added or changed a verse or the music as a way of showing she isn't the same person anymore and has been through so much in life, but is feeling like she is in the same place once again. That would have been really special.</p>

<p>I see none of that, feel none of it, instead I hear what is mostly the same song but with a weird, intangible emptiness to it. It is the same song as from 2008, recorded in a new studio with a new, perhaps better, production team. I find myself unable to relate to this 31 year old multi-millionaire pop sensation "Taylor Swift" the same way I could relate to the 18 year old "Taylor" who I felt was just like me all those years ago. To me, it doesn't feel like it is coming from her, or from a place of genuine feeling and desire to produce art. It feels commercial, like a cover of her own song from so many years ago, or maybe even like a very popular artist covering a song from a young upstart, doing an impressive job technically but without touching its emotional core. I can't help but feel this is coming less from her than from the record label looking to cash in on the nostalgia and the adoration of her fans, many of whom have expressed delight in seeing her "return to her roots" with the last two albums, in a way. Perhaps this is cynical. It feels less like "Taylor's Version" and more like Scholastic/Bloomsbury pushing new print runs of the Harry Potter books, this time with fancy foil covers or Hogwarts house-themed binding in the hopes that people throw money at it again. Perhaps it is unfair to her, and perhaps I see capitalism as a boogeyman in every corner. Or perhaps commercialization is something that has existed in the music industry as long as the term "industry" was appended to the music. Maybe this is part and parcel of life as an artist and it is unfair to project your expectations onto an artist you like, expecting them to cater to your very specific and very unimportant ideals.</p>

<p>In the epilogue to Brandon Sanderson's "Words of Radiance", a chapter also titled "Art and Expectation", he writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Art...is fundamentally unfair.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Expectation. That is the true soul of art. If you can give a man more than he expects, then he will laud you his entire life. If you can create an air of anticipation and feed it properly, you will succeed.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Conversely, if you gain a reputation for being too good, too skilled ... beware. The better art will be in their heads, and if you give them an ounce less than they imagined, suddenly you have failed.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I've discussed the way I feel about this new song with other fans and received some measure of pushback. And I get it. It <em>is</em> nitpicking. I <em>am</em> being unfair to her by expecting something she never promised in the first place, and I am perhaps being critical of something I don't deserve the right to critique. I still can't help but feel this way. The song still rings hollow to me. I can't see the same innocence and naivete in it that I did in the original, and that perhaps is more on me than it is on Taylor Swift. </p>

<p>I think long and hard before documenting my visceral reactions to music this way, because the last time I did was in 2017, soon after Linkin Park released "One More Light". Like several fans at the time, I didn't like the album. I saw firsthand as the poor reception poured out across social media, talk about how the band was a shell of its former self, how they were pushing out new music without thinking beyond their own pockets, how it was a completely different band and so on. Two months later, Chester Bennington was found dead. While a reason for his suicide has not been confirmed, I cannot help but feel that this toxic culture of entitlement I enabled and participated in to some extent could have played a part in it. I'm still very conflicted putting this post out because I don't want to be in that situation again. I might take it down later. This love is difficult, but it's real.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Reclaim Control Over Your Content Consumption with RSS Feeds</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/use-rss-feeds.html</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021</pubDate>
<description>RSS feeds have been around forever, and remain as relevant today as they were years ago. They might be a way out of the social dillemma, and here's how you can start using them.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is part 1 in a two-part series on RSS feeds.</p>

<p>The early internet was, I believe, truly ahead of its time. We have a lot more eye candy and fancy functionality today, that's for sure, but some of the most enduring ideas at the foundation of the internet are just a little younger than the internet itself. One of these is the RSS feed. No
matter what your site is, what content you post, or how it looks, an RSS feed is able to standardize its contents into a single XML file that can then be used to track updates, or what we have come to call "follow" you.</p>

<p>My understanding is that RSS feed usage peaked during the peak of Google Reader in the mid-2000s. It seems to have all been downhill since then. Today, RSS has a small but faithful fanbase, and though it is seeing a silent resurgence by being the backend for podcasts, it has largely been
relegated to oblivion. I feel like there are two major reasons to this. </p>

<p>The first is that RSS being simple yet flexible means it affords a great deal of control to the site owner as well as the follower over how they want to follow and consume content. You can view the entire post without leaving your feed reader, or can see a short summary and then jump straight to the site to read the rest of the post. This freedom and control is antithetical to the foundation of modern social networks, which rely heavily on addictive patterns and engaging UX shenanigans to keep you immersed and engaged on the platform for as long as possible. They need you to let them curate what you see, and to keep scrolling so they can serve you ads and make money off you. It was never about the content, or at least it hasn't been for a while and is likely never going to be
unless the economic structures underlying these systems are overhauled completely. </p>

<p>The second, less controversial reason is that the web is just a lot more diverse than it was before. It can be hard to reduce an entire website to a single feed of updates, although it really shouldn't be and this feels like a design flaw that can be remedied today itself. It is of course worth making a distinction between the "document web"- your news sites, blogs, personal websites, job listings, classifieds and so on- and the "application web"- intensive, interactive applications that aren't just read-only and typically require user input. The application web certainly has a place in the online landscape, but the document web undoubtedly deserves to be simpler to browse and access.</p>

<p>If you want to escape the social dillemma and regain control over your consumption habits, there is nothing better than RSS. Here's how you can get started.</p>

<p><strong>Picking a client</strong></p>

<p>You need a client to view RSS feeds, and there are some great options out there for any platform of your choice.</p>

<p>Cross-platform: There's a lot of cross-platform RSS services that let you follow your news and subscriptions on any device of your choosing, and even sync reading history so you are always up to date and never see any redundant information. Of these, my recommendations are <a href="https://tt-rss.org/">TinyTinyRSS</a> or <a href="https://miniflux.app/">Miniflux</a> if you can self-host, or <a href="https://theoldreader.com/">TheOldReader</a>, <a href="https://bazqux.com/">BazQux</a>, <a href="https://feedly.com/">Feedly</a>, <a href="https://www.inoreader.com/">InoReader</a> and <a href="https://www.newsblur.com/">NewsBlur</a> otherwise. All very solid services.</p>

<p>Desktop: For Windows, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/p/newsflow/9nblggh58s5r?activetab=pivot:overviewtab">NewsFlow</a> seems to be a pretty good option. Mac users can use <a href="https://www.reederapp.com/">Reeder</a>, which is pretty popular. Linux users have quite a few options available to them. For a more traditional GUI experience, I recommend <a href="https://gitlab.com/news-flash/news_flash_gtk">NewsFlash</a>, <a href="https://lzone.de/liferea/">Liferea</a> or <a href="https://quiterss.org/">QuiteRSS</a>. However, terminal users will find a lot of value in <a href="https://newsboat.org/">newsboat</a> or <a href="https://github.com/skeeto/elfeed">elfeed</a> if you use emacs.</p>

<p>Mobile: On Android, the best reader I have found is <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.frju.flym&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US">Flym</a>. <a href="https://www.reederapp.com/">Reeder</a> (linked above for MacOS) has an iOS client as well. If you're using any cross-platform service, their app/PWA is likely to be good too, and some 3rd party clients also let you hook them up to these services to sync your reading history.</p>

<p><strong>Finding RSS Feeds</strong></p>

<p>Modern RSS readers and services have search inbuilt that will let you add several sources without having to context-switch. A lot of sites you go to will put the RSS feed up front, typically in a header/footer or on the front page. However, this may not be true for quite a few sites due to the declining influence of RSS on the modern web. Fear not; all is not lost. A number of sites just have so much content that they might not put up the RSS link in a noticeable spot, or might just leave it in the source but not advertise it at all. Several websites are built on modern content management systems that all provide RSS feeds, while others still follow standard web practices and can be scraped to create feeds. It is worth trying the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>Add a /feed, or /rss, or /rss.xml or /feed.rss to the URL and see if it returns an XML file.</li>
<li>On desktop, view the source for the site's front page and Ctrl+F to search for the words "feed". "rss", or "atom".</li>
<li>For reddit, you can add a ".rss" to the URL for any subreddit to get a feed for it.</li>
<li>HackerNews RSS feeds are available at <a href="https://hnrss.org">HNRSS</a></li>
<li>Finally, you can use <a href="https://rssbox.herokuapp.com/">RSSBox</a>, <a href="https://rss.app/">rss.app</a>, or <a href="http://fetchrss.com/">FetchRSS</a> to generate feeds for a variety of sites, social networks, and other services. The likes of <a href="https://www.datorss.com/">dato.rss</a> are also pretty useful if you want to search for feeds.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>By relying on social media and big tech to curate our feeds for us, we become subservient to them, and very willing to stay within the bubbles they create for us. You can use RSS to reclaim this control, curate your own feeds, and read on your own terms. </p>

<p>PS: If you're running a site of your own, keep an eye out for my next post, where I highlight how you can add an RSS feed to your site.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Crypto- A Regret and A Request</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/crypto-regret-request.html</link>
<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021</pubDate>
<description>Musings on rolling your own crypto and my academic misadventures.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In my second year in university as a CS major, I pitched an academic paper to an IEEE conference along with three colleagues. The paper highlighted a "novel" symmetric encryption scheme that we'd spent the better part of the summer brainstorming. It wasn't without its merits, and seemed to fulfill <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/kryptosgrapheinen/overview/objectives">the absolute basics of cryptography</a> well enough. We mostly thought of it as a toy project, and went ahead to make an encrypted chat application, where keys were generated on the initiating device and shared to the recipient via an implementation of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diffie%E2%80%93Hellman_key_exchange">Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange</a>. At the time, everyone involved was rather excited about it, and while we didn't think of ourselves as cryptographic pioneers, having the paper accepted certainly was a matter of pride and added what we felt was some legitimacy to our efforts.</p>

<p>It took some time before my interest in security and privacy led me to realize the issues with what we had cooked up. It was slow, and lacked forward secrecy in any form whatsoever, and that was just the beginning. We hadn't yet come across the tenet that <a href="https://resources.infosecinstitute.com/topic/the-dangers-of-rolling-your-own-encryption/">you don't roll your own crypto.</a> Toy projects are fine, they're educational and can help you understand a lot of things that lectures might not. But these ideas once cemented, if encouraged unconditionally, legitimized, and not corrected, can lead to any of us deploying their own ham-fisted encryption in a production application, and that can have disastrous consequences.</p>

<p>Quoting <a href="https://www.cryptofails.com/post/75204435608/write-crypto-code-dont-publish-it">this excellent CryptoFails article</a>,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Donald Rumsfeld said this:</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p><em>There are known knowns. These are things we know that we know. There are known unknowns. That is to say, there are things that we know we don’t know. But there are also unknown unknowns. These are things that we don’t know we don’t know.</em></p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I hypothesize that most crypto errors, especially the ones at the design level, are “unknown unknowns” to the designer.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Quoting <a href="https://soatok.blog/2021/01/20/please-stop-encrypting-with-rsa-directly/">another excellent article on why RSA is a bad idea to use as a primary encryption scheme</a>,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>First, consider not using RSA. Hell, while you’re at it, don’t write any cryptography code that you don’t have to.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Libsodium (which you should use) does most of this for you, and can easily be turned into an AKE comparable to the one Signal uses. The less cryptography code you have to write, the less can go catastrophically wrong–especially in production systems.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you are an educator, a supervisor, a reviewer, please encourage students to think critically about cryptography and devise new cryptosystems for fun, but also remind them that standing on the shoulders of giants is a good thing, especially when mission-critical systems depend on it. If you're a student or someone just starting out, I point you towards the title of the Cryptofails article linked above: <em>Write Crypto Code! Don't Publish It.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Signal: Down, but Not Out</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/signal-down.html</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021</pubDate>
<description>Signal is down, should you leave? (please don't)</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25793483">Signal services were down</a> at night (IST) on Friday, 15th January, 2021.</p>

<p>As of the time this article goes up, services remain suspended. People who have moved their entire, or a sizable portion of their networks over recently are grasping at ways to contact each other again, some falling back to greener pastures like WhatsApp, and others looking for alternatives already.</p>

<p>I'm not saying this is acceptable. I understand the criticality that often comes with instant messaging, and the problems that arise if networks suddenly collapse on you. It may well be a matter of life and death in some hopefully rare but unfortunate cases. The situation is far from ideal, but the optimist in me still believes.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/signalapp/status/1349577579091566592#m">Signal's user base grew almost 4x over just a few days this week</a>, and traffic on the app likely grew by an order of magnitude more. Growing pains are expected when dealing with problems on this scale, and I absolutely believe things will be looking up soon again. If it is a scaling issue, it may well need to be fixed just this once. As the curve of new users onboarding themselves as well as the traffic flattens (or gets less steep) over time, such issues will be fewer and further apart. </p>

<p>It is worth remembering that even services that are backed by some of the largest corporations in the world like WhatsApp <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/news/whatsapp-down-not-working-app-iphone-android-ios-loading-issue-problem-a8741301.html">have been down similarly</a> less than a year ago, and have experienced scaling issues during the pandemic as more people find themselves online than ever before. This too, I must believe, shall pass.</p>

<p>This is not to say that you shouldn't keep both eyes open at all times. See how things go, and if it seems like the service is unable to keep up even after you've given it enough chances in the near or distant future, you absolutely should consider picking alternatives, perhaps even decentralized services like XMPP or Matrix that are less likely to suffer from such issues.</p>

<p>I must remind anyone reading this that Signal is not run by bloodthirsty corporations, and it does not seek to make products of its users. Signal runs on the time and effort every volunteer puts in, and the support of patrons and donors. If there is one thing you do in response to this outage, <a href="https://signal.org/donate">please let it be a gesture of support</a>.</p>

<p>This is not the time to jump back to what feels safe and familiar. We must hold strong for a better tomorrow.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>GitHub Pages to Neocities, a New Home</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/gh-to-neocities.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021</pubDate>
<description>My blog has a new home now, and it's wonderful.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today, I moved this website over from GitHub Pages to Neocities. </p>

<p>There's not much to the decision, really. There are several hosting options for static sites like GH Pages, GitLab Pages, Netlify, and now even Cloudflare Pages. Anyone starting out should be more than fine picking any of these options. But here's what drew me to Neocities.</p>

<p>When you use Neocities, it is extremely evident that they are a "little guy" company that puts its values up front for everyone to see, and backs them up by making the source freely available for anyone to audit and augment. There's very little "marketing speak" because it's not really a product. When they say <em>Neocities is bringing back the fun, creativity and independence that made the web great</em>, you want to believe them, and a click on the "Websites" button in the header gives you exactly that belief.</p>

<p>It's beautiful, wild, completely chaotic and hard to believe as something one would see in 2020. No two sites look the same, and it feels like a rudimentary social network in the craziest way possible. There are glowing reviews for everyone to see on sites like Hacker News, and it is wickedly easy to get started and to set up a site. That said, surface simplicity does not mean it is in any way a shallow product or inferior to the other static hosts, at least for basic use cases. No ads or tracking anywhere to be seen, free HTTPS for all sites on the platform, and they even run a CDN with 11 datacenters. I'm not sure anyone can really ask for more, especially considering the free tier is extremely generous and will likely be more than most users need. </p>

<p>Moving my site over was really easy. I could have just used the upload options on the dashboard, but I set up a git hook and configured the site in under 5 minutes. This may not be the last destination for my site; indeed I would love to have my own domain some time in the future, but I don't have the funds or really the justification to go there yet.</p>

<p>My workflow remains almost entirely unchanged, as does the experience for any visitors to the site. But I get to keep a smug grin on my face, thinking about being a part of something that is exciting and wonderful. I'm not sure one can ask for more.</p>

<p><em>Update: As of 21st February 2021, this website is now on its own domain and no longer on Neocities. The allure of owning my own online presence was too good for me to pass up. My short stint on neocities was extremely positive and I still recommend it without any qualms to anyone who wants to host static websites for free. It remains one of my favourite projects on the internet and I wish them nothing but the best. I'm very satisfied with my hosting solution at the moment, but in a future where I can afford the $5 per month supporter fee for Neocities, I would absolutely consider retaining my custom domain and switching to them for static hosting so I can support this excellent platform.</em> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Why I Don't Use Telegram</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/why-i-dont-use-telegram.html</link>
<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021</pubDate>
<description>In light of recent events, people are dropping WhatsApp. Here's why Telegram is a bad choice for your messaging needs.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>WhatsApp recently rolled out <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/01/whatsapp-users-must-share-their-data-with-facebook-or-stop-using-the-app/">changes to its privacy policy</a> that highlight how user data is shared with Facebook in a common pool of data from all Facebook-owned services. While this just sheds light on practices that one must assume have been in play since WhatsApp was acquired by Facebook 6 years ago, putting it front and center seems to have been enough to give a not-insignificant portion of its user base a sense of unease. A number of people have chosen to move to other messaging applications, either dropping WhatsApp entirely or at least shifting as much of their network over to other platforms as possible. While this is an admirable pursuit, one that I have been vocally in favour of for the last few years, there are still good and bad options among the available alternatives.</p>

<p>If the title wasn't clear enough, I don't believe Telegram is a good fit for a WhatsApp replacement if you are a privacy-conscious individual. I believe it is a significant security downgrade, and potentially a privacy liability as well.</p>

<p>On WhatsApp, <a href="https://scontent.whatsapp.net/v/t39.8562-34/122249142_469857720642275_2152527586907531259_n.pdf/WA_Security_WhitePaper.pdf?ccb=2&amp;_nc_sid=2fbf2a&amp;_nc_ohc=U4i2jUSaMEwAX9Ol7xO&amp;_nc_ht=scontent.whatsapp.net&amp;oh=4d42dd5c20af7304e1a49494c9fd5ced&amp;oe=601B0C99">all chats are end-to-end encrypted</a> using their implementation of the <a href="https://www.signal.org/docs/">Signal protocol</a>. Of course, WhatsApp is proprietary software and you have pretty much only their word for it. That said, the Signal protocol itself is very well defined and has <a href="https://github.com/signalapp/libsignal-protocol-c">implementations available under GPLv3</a>. It comes down to whether you trust WhatsApp to implement said encryption without incompetence or malice (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanlon%27s_razor">Hanlon's Razor</a>). Being owned by Facebook leaves significant room for malice, I suppose, but less so for incompetence considering they have the talent and resources of one of the largest corporations in the world behind them. Ultimately, a matter of trust.</p>

<p>Telegram, on the other hand, have gone ahead and released the <a href="https://telegram.org/apps#source-code">sources for all their clients</a> on Github under GPLv2, as reproducible builds too. This is commendable and should be the standard for any app that performs such critical functions for millions of users. It allows discerning users to verify that their messages are indeed encrypted as stated by the specification before they leave their device, for instance. Yet, this does not alleviate the issues with the platform as they would like you to believe. </p>

<p>First, Telegram's developers have made an active choice to drop end-to-end encryption for the bulk of messaging on their platform, <a href="https://telegra.ph/Why-Isnt-Telegram-End-to-End-Encrypted-by-Default-08-14">stating creature comforts like ease of backing up</a> as the reason for doing so. For most 1-1 chats and ALL group chats on the platform, Telegram use a <a href="https://core.telegram.org/mtproto">"server-client" encryption scheme</a> that essentially allows for in-transit encryption between your device and their servers, which is effective against <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack">MITM attacks</a>, but involves keys generated and controlled by Telegram themselves as part of an exchange between your device and their servers. End-to-end encryption is provided for 1-1 chats in the form of their <a href="https://core.telegram.org/api/end-to-end">"secret messages" feature</a>, but it being only an option tends to mean very low adoption, not to mention the fact that this courtesy isn't even extended for group conversations where it is perhaps needed more. The secret chats feature is also entirely unavailable on the desktop or web versions of the Telegram client. The purpose of end-to-end encryption is that only the sender and the intended recipient are able to see the contents of the message, and the medium over which it is sent is essentially taken out of the equation if the encryption is strong enough. This is very clearly not the case with Telegram by design.</p>

<p>While apps like WhatsApp and Signal choose not to retain any of your messages on their servers once they are delivered successfully, Telegram back up all your messages to their servers and retain them indefinitely, for the stated purpose of allowing near-instant cloud sync for your message database across all your devices no matter where you are. This stated purpose it achieves with flying colours, but with some (in my opinion significant) compromise to privacy. For all their assurances about encryption and all their declarations of open-sourced clients, you end up in a similar situation to WhatsApp where you have to trust the channel (Telegram servers) to not deal with your messages with malicious intent. Telegram's own site states <a href="https://telegram.org/privacy#4-1-storing-data">"All data is stored heavily encrypted so that local Telegram engineers or physical intruders cannot get access"</a>, a claim that is tenuous given the encrypted-at-rest content is on servers controlled by them and so are the keys to decrypt them. You are relying on their goodwill to handle your data with the utmost integrity at all times, a situation that would not have arisen if your chats were verifiably end-to-end encrypted. Further, such a claim is also impossible to verify since Telegram have not open-sourced the code for their servers, and even if they had, there is no way you can verify that the provided code is what is running on their servers, and no more. This is the case with Signal as well, even though they provide their server code freely.</p>

<p>It is true that WhatsApp decrypts their backups before uploading to cloud storage like Google Drive and iCloud, and this is a major vulnerability since even if you yourself have disabled these backups, as long as those you interact with have them enabled, your messages are available in what is essentially plaintext for at least two parties (Facebook and Google/Apple) to use as they please. It goes without saying that this is a privacy nightmare, especially since all 3 concerned corporations have been known to be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRISM_%28surveillance_program%29">willing to collaborate</a> with governments in some capacity in the past, and likely would again of their own volition or under sufficient duress. That said, it seems unlikely that sacrificing e2e encryption is the only choice that would allow you to avoid such a situation, like Telegram would have you believe. While "instant sync" may not be achievable, it does not seem like it is completely impossible to create multipart fully end-to-end encrypted containers that are then backed up to the cloud, only decryptable on either end with the local keys. WhatsApp themselves have a key transference/new key association with each profile procedure in place if you are switching devices.</p>

<p>In recent years Telegram has earned renown for pushing back against government agencies across the world who have sought personal data from them, to the extent that the application has been banned in some jurisdictions and deplatformed in others. Again, however, it is a situation totally at their mercy, one that can be changed if Pavel Durov or other people in positions of power in their hierarchy change their mind, or in the event of a buyout to people with more questionable morals. Further, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/6/18/21295535/russia-telegram-ban-lifted-security">Russia recently lifted their ban on Telegram, their telecom watchdog Roskomnadzor said the company had expressed willingness in assisting them in their counterterrorism efforts</a>. However you feel about the Russian government and whether or not this reeks of collusion is entirely up for interpretation and likely not verifiable, but it would not be the case if the option to do so was never given to Telegram.</p>

<p>And yet the problems do not end here.</p>

<p>In a <a href="https://t.me/durov/145">blog post</a>, no doubt attempting to grab some attention given recent events, Telegram creator Pavel Durov claims "Our encryption and API are fully documented and have been reviewed by security experts thousands of times." It is curious that in a post where he cites a number of references to put down competitors to his app, he provides no citations to this claim. </p>

<p>Further, Durov attempts to sully the Signal protocol by calling it "an encryption protocol funded by the US Government", as if that alone is tantamount to some kind of secret backdoor they've paid for, or association with government funding itself disqualifies it from any discussion about security. This, of course, is borderline conspiracy theory, considering the Signal protocol along with its implementation in Signal's own app has been open and available for years, having survived <a href="https://community.signalusers.org/t/wiki-overview-of-third-party-security-audits/13243">multiple rounds of audits</a> to the extent of being considered reliable and secure by security experts the world over. The same cannot be said about Telegram's own MTProto algorithm, which was initially received very poorly perhaps due to the maxim "You don't roll your own crypto" popular in the infosec community. There are multiple <a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2015/1177.pdf">studies</a> and articles that were critical of its implementation and of the hype surrounding it like the fact that they decided <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180420061726/http://unhandledexpression.com/2013/12/17/telegram-stand-back-we-know-maths/">having a bunch of PhD's on their team was testament to its security</a> , or the <a href="https://archive.vn/SIl9M">enormous bounty someone who found a vulnerability in the system would receive</a>. A <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20181118154823/https://www.alexrad.me/discourse/a-264-attack-on-telegram-and-why-a-super-villain-doesnt-need-it-to-read-your-telegram-chats.html">2^64 attack</a> was also theorized against Telegram in 2015. These are events in the 2013-16 period, and many of the criticisms may not be valid now. Telegram themselves have released a new version dubbed MTProto 2.0, but the thousands of reviews Durov alludes to are certainly not forthcoming after a cursory web search for "MTProto 2 audit" and similar terms, except <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/346702021_Automated_Symbolic_Verification_of_Telegram%27s_MTProto_20">one that seems overall positive</a>, which is good. I am not a cryptanalyst myself so I do not have an opinion on MTProto, but I wish to highlight some of the hype surrounding the application, much of which comes from the horse's mouth. Durov is very quick to proclaim that Telegram does not spend on marketing, but it is worth remembering that it does not mean that they do not indulge in marketing.</p>

<p>I have some other reservations about the app that prevent me from using it, one of which is the <a href="https://telegram.org/blog/unsend-privacy-emoji">"delete everywhere"</a> feature, that allows you to delete any message in a conversation from your device as well as that of the other party. On the surface, this seems alright, especially since apps like WhatsApp and Signal allow you to do this too. However, Telegram differs from them in two key areas. First, Telegram allows you to not only delete messages you have <em>sent</em> "for everyone", but also ones that you have <em>received</em>. Secondly, while WhatsApp and Signal choose to have a placeholder in the message bubble on the lines of "this message was deleted" to show that a message used to exist but has now been deleted, Telegram removes any trace of its existence altogether, from the devices of everyone involved in the conversation. In true Telegram fashion, this too was branded as returning <em>complete control</em> on conversations to all their users, because private data is "sacred" to them. They fail to recognize, or do realize and outright ignore the fact that giving a recipient control over a message they have not sent and allowing them to delete it from both ends means control is taken away from the sender. Further, the fact that messages can be deleted without trace leaves a horrible taste in my mouth, as it is ripe for gaslighting and getting rid of evidence in serious matters. I cannot, in good conscience, use an app that allows this to happen.</p>

<p>All this said, it would be unfair to say Telegram is entirely insecure or that its developers have made a bad application with no thought put into its security. As is the case with everything in life, there is nuance to it, and they have chosen to trade convenience for security/privacy in several instances. If your threat model is okay with these compromises, Telegram may well be the most engaging, fluid, and featureful instant messaging platform you can find. Personally, it is not for me, and I choose to keep my messages on <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal</a>, and have tried <a href="https://briarproject.org/">Briar</a> (peer-to-peer, decentralized, e2ee) and <a href="https://matrix.org/">Matrix</a> (decentralized, p2p available, e2ee available) recently. No messaging app is perfect, and trade-offs like the ones Telegram made exist on each of these, although the options I prefer do tend to value security and privacy over convenience in most aspects. I do continue to use WhatsApp simply because network effects (<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/26/whatsapp-india-users-400-million/">India is WhatsApp's largest market in the world</a>) have made it so that most of my contacts as well as professional groups use WhatsApp as their platform.</p>

<p>I've tried to do my due diligence while writing this article but would absolutely appreciate being proven wrong in any of my claims or being provided any information that proves useful in evaluating the viability of Telegram or any oftheir competing platforms. Please free to contact me with the information on this site, and I will put up corrections to this article if pointed out. Until next time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Bucking Social Media Attraction with Light Frontends</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/alt-social-frontends.html</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021</pubDate>
<description>Alternative frontends for popular social networks.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My struggles with social media are long-standing and will likely wage on for years to come (separate post about that later perhaps). That said, I was looking for ways to minimize the time I spend on any social sites across all my devices. Unfortunately, my friends send me links to things on Reddit and Twitter that I am interested in or need to read to be part of the conversation, and there are other cases like checking the match thread on r/chelseafc when one of our matches is on that I like doing and want to continue doing. The problem this poses is that on desktop it is easy to get sucked in if you are logged onto your own account because one thing will lead to another and you will (or at least I do) find yourself on your feed doomscrolling. Another problem is that these sites are just freaking terrible. Even without the absurd amounts of tracking (Reddit, or new Reddit at least, seems to log mouse movements too), the experience is just full of cruft and really slow and irritating. The mobile web experience is downright hostile, especially if you are not logged in. I really didn't want to keep these apps installed on my phone, and finally I don't have to.</p>

<p>There are alternative frontends for each of these sites that are at the very least acceptable, or in my opinion significantly superior to the original sites. Here are the ones I use:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://nitter.net">Nitter</a> for Twitter</li>
<li><a href="https://teddit.net">Teddit</a> for Reddit</li>
<li><a href="https://bibliogram.art">Bibliogram</a> for Instagram</li>
<li><a href="https://invidious.snopyta.org/">Invidious</a> (now kind of abandonware) and <a href="https://freetubeapp.io/">FreeTube</a> for YouTube</li>
</ul>

<p>The advantages are manifold. Firstly, these are really fast and almost all features work without JavaScript enabled (Teddit iirc doesn't use JS at all). This makes them ideal for mobile usage even on shitty mobile net, and I also tend to do all my general purpose web browsing in a firefox profile that has JavaScript blocked. Further, they don't rely on the actual website or their APIs, which reduces the amount of tracking they can do to some extent. Finally, and this part is more important than I realized, they don't need you to, and in fact don't have any option for you to log into your account. This means no tailored feed, no urge to vote or indulge in comment flame wars, and no doomscrolling for the most part. </p>

<p>Those interested in trying these can use the <a href="https://github.com/SimonBrazell/privacy-redirect">Privacy Redirect</a> extension on your browser of choice. I was using it until recently but have now switched to the more powerful <a href="https://github.com/einaregilsson/Redirector">Redirector</a> that lets me set up custom rules as I'd like. I also have the extension installed with these settings on my mobile Firefox browser.</p>

<p>When someone sends me these links, I have them load up in these alternate sites by default without any effort, and I can close it out once I'm done. Short of ditching the sites entirely, this is perhaps the sanest alternative.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>On Letting Go</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/on-letting-go.html</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020</pubDate>
<description>How my life changed when I gave up a structured approach for some pursuits</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The year was 2017. I was fresh off reading almost a hundred books in the previous year and raring to go again. My to-read lists on Goodreads and in notebooks and excel spreadsheets were overflowing with entries, most of them likely to be enjoyable. I was taking pride in being called "well-read" by peers, and just about beginning to feel the same way about myself. But I wasn't happy.</p>

<p>In hindsight, it's easy to say I made a change in my life because I wasn't happy, but the truth is I never know if I'm happy or not on a given day. I just <em>am</em>. But I remember clear as day that on a particular day in 2017, I got rid of every single list I had. They were deleted, cast aside, and banished to oblivion. If you asked me why that day, I'd probably say <em>because I could.</em> </p>

<p><em>Pudge, what you must understand about me is that I am a deeply unhappy person</em>, says a John Green character in Looking for Alaska. I suppose the part of me left buried in his body of work, the part I shamelessly resuscitated while watching the series adaptation of Looking for Alaska for Hulu, would likely refer to himself in a similar fashion. In many ways, it was true and perhaps still is. I've enjoyed reading since I picked up the habit at 4 or 5 years old. I've read hundreds of books, carried stacks of books home from the school library that the librarian would challenge me I wouldn't finish by the due date (I always won), and relentlessly pursued books in every shape or form I could find. But on that day in 2017, I felt like I didn't enjoy reading. That I wasn't reading for reading's sake, for enjoyment, for fulfillment, or for entertainment. I felt like I was reading to put numbers on a list- to be able to brag to a Facebook group that I was admin of at the time that I'd actually outread several of them that year, that somehow my being this prolific made me smarter, superior, better than them. And I'd probably get away with saying that I gave up this pursuit out of the goodness of my heart, realizing the poor grasp of reality that I held on so dearly to. Alas, introspection is a boon that comes in trickles to men of moderate privilege like myself, and my boon felt it was enough to let me know that I was exhausted trying to live up to this perception of myself.</p>

<p>And so, it was done. I made a vow to myself that I would read only on my own terms, and that I'd follow a laissez-faire approach to any literary pursuits I follow and live a little vicariously, without the pressures that structures might impose. How do I feel about it 3 years later? There is some wistfulness about the whole "so many books in the world, so little time" shtick- certainly I've read fewer and fewer books year-on-year. Of course, surrounding conditions haven't necessarily enabled literary voracity, but that's alright because I had no targets, no expectations. Just a world of literature waiting for me to reach out. I don't think of myself as well-read anymore, but I've made peace with it. I enjoyed most of what I've read and am finding my way back to establishing a healthy reading habit. </p>

<p>Probably couldn't have asked for more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>On Reinventing the Wheel</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/on-reinventing-the-wheel.html</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020</pubDate>
<description>Or, why I did what I did with this site</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25227181">On an interesting thread in HN today</a>, there was much discussion on the idea of reinventing the wheel in software projects and writing one's own static site generators. As someone fresh out of college where reinventing the wheel is not only encouraged but mandated in several areas to learn concepts, and also as someone who has "written" their own "static site generator", I feel like it's worth exploring this a little.</p>

<p>I've had blogs in some shape or form before. Blogger, WordPress, Ghost, and more recently Jekyll, Hugo and Zola. On the surface they all produce a good enough output, and have a ton of features. I could have stuck to any of them and called it a day, I'm sure the tens of thousands (?) of bloggers who do aren't particularly dissatisfied with their weapon of choice, mostly because they have bigger things to be concerned about, like the content. And yet, I'm happier with my solution today than I ever was with any of these, and here's why:</p>

<p>I've found that for simple blogs, especially hobby projects, you don't really need a WYSIWYG editor or an elaborate design or all kinds of funky tools, plugins and features that established CMS tools provide. Hell, I believe most of them don't even need to load several hundred kilobytes to a few megabytes of JavaScript to the user for eye-candy/obscure features either. If you can serve a static page with some minimal styling for readability, it's incredibly lightweight, likely doesn't need a CDN to be served quickly to viewers, and is just good design in general. This is my argument for using a static site generator. But why your own? </p>

<p>I've found the Unix philosophy to be a nice guideline for a number of decisions in life. This is true for a blog workflow as well:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Let each component do one thing, and do it well</em>: Posts are text files, written entirely in a text editor. The static site generator exclusively takes the post content and turns it into HTML. </p></li>
<li><p><em>Expect the output of every program to become the input to another</em>: Again, posts are text files. They can be fed into any template for any formatting for the final site. The outputted HTML can be viewed locally in a browser as a file, served on a local server for live refresh, and uploaded directly to GitHub/GitLab pages or your own site for hosting. Each component's involvement is only in one step of the process, and each component is designed to be replaceable should it stop working or should a better option present itself in the near future. For instance, I could use something other than Markdown for formatting text, something other than vim for editing, something other than Python (or indeed the entire generator) for building the site, and some other hosting provider for, well, for hosting it.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>What these afford is simplicity- I get to know exactly what every step of my blog workflow does, and extensibility- if I want more features I can code them myself or seek assistance or contributions from the community. I prefer this minimal approach to the jack of all trades approach where the tool you use is already full of features you may never need, but they're there if you need them. This is why I wrote my own generator instead of using the several awesome ones available. There are merits to both approaches and I wouldn't be surprised that for commercial endeavours the established tools likely do the job better, are more reliable, and save time, effort, and money 90% of the time. And yet there are power users who swear by their own solution since they know it end-to-end and are not held back by arbitrary limitations of some other platform.</p>

<p>I end this ramble with some quotes from the HN thread, with credit.</p>

<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25249963">arpyzo's comment</a></p>

<p><em>I completely understand the desire to build something practical that's your own.
I just built a small web application framework that I can build some basic personal apps on top of. Just like the author's, it's "shitty". It lacks features, doesn't handle edge cases, isn't particularly secure or performant.
None of that matters. It's locked up behind HTTP authentication and it's for my use only. It has exactly the features I desire, and none that I don't. I understand it top to bottom. It was fun to write and extend. It serves my needs perfectly. I didn't have to fight with, or conform to someone else's notion of how software should be built.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25251110">411111111111111's comment</a></p>

<p><em>"don't reinvent the wheel" is specifically for projects which other people will be forced to maintain.
You can reinvent the wheel as many times you want. If you however do that at work, your colleagues and your replacement after you left the job likely won't think too kindly of you.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25250012">bogwog's comment</a></p>

<p><em>I spent about a day migrating my personal site from grav to hugo, and the main takeaway I got from that experience is that both of these "simple" static site generators are ridiculously over-engineered.
I could slap something together with a few lines of Make or Python that does exactly what I need, in an hour or two. I could even hook it up to AWS and have it update automatically.
Doing all of that is less time consuming and requires less effort than reading through the grav or hugo documentation, installing and setting everything up, and troubleshooting the inevitable problems.
The only issue I have is that doing front-end web development/design is not something I enjoy, so grav and hugo's existing library of themes is very convenient. Convenient enough to put up with the other annoyances.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25250648">JasonFruit's comment</a></p>

<p><em>For me, the reason was simpler: it took less effort to write an SSG than it did to learn any existing one, and I got the fun of doing it.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Tags are a thing now, I guess</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/tags.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2020</pubDate>
<description>The super-basic static site generator I wrote now supports tags.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In case you don't know, I've been writing <a href="https://github.com/RonitRay/ecstatic">my own static site generator in Python</a> to generate this site. The initial codebase was borrowed with thanks from <a href="https://blog.naveeraashraf.com/posts/make-static-site-generator-with-python/">Naveera Ashraf's very helpful blog post</a>. I have since put in some of my own code to implement the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>A homepage template with some formatting to show a bio and some relevant links aside from the blog feed. This works pretty well as a homepage for a personal site and is extensible to include fancy CSS and JS if someone is so inclined.</li>
<li><p>One of the features mentioned in their post was:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>One more thing that I want to do is to have the tags of each post in some kind of list so I can loop through them as I may want to make each tag into a clickable link</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The way they chose to implement it was to generate the tags for each post and display them as buttons below the post, but what one did with those buttons was up to them. Which is fair, but I wanted to build a system that could pick up unique tags and generate multiple separate pages of posts relevant to each tag. This is something that would have been trivial to do with some JS filtering, but I was adamant on keeping this site static, light and JS-free until I really needed it so I wanted a workaround and wrote one.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>A set of unique tags is built after scanning each post.</p>

<div class="codeblock">
<pre><code class='language-python'>
python tags = []; 
for post in posts_metadata: 
    if post['blog']=='yes': 
        tags.extend(post['tags'].split(', ')); 
tags=list(set(tags)); 
tags.sort();
</code></pre>
</div></li>
<li><p>There is a 'tag' template that is meant to display all posts for a particular tag, which are passed to it by the generator.</p>

<div class="codeblock">
<pre><code class='language-html'>   
{% for post in tagposts %}
{% if post.blog == 'yes' %}
    &lt;p&gt; {{post.date}} | &lt;a href="posts/{{ post.slug }}.html"&gt;{{post.title}}&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
{% endif %}
{% endfor %}
</code></pre>
</div></li>
<li><p>This tag page is generated in my main generator program for every unique tag. We loop through the posts, find whether their tag list contains a particular tag, and then pass it in the list of posts to the template if it does.</p>

<div class="codeblock">
<pre><code class='language-python'>
tag_template = env.get_template('tag.html')
for tag in tags:
    tagposts_metadata = [POSTS[post].metadata for post in POSTS if tag in POSTS[post].metadata['tags'].split(', ')]
    tag_html = tag_template.render(tagposts=tagposts_metadata, tag=tag)
    with open('output/posts/tag-'+tag+'.html', 'w') as file:
        file.write(tag_html)
</code></pre>
</div></li>
</ol></li>
</ol>

<p>Since all of the generation is done on my development/writing machine, only the static output is published to the site and it loads as fast as any static HTML for the user, no unnecessary CPU hogging needed. I'm almost positive this code is suboptimal because it's literally a quick and dirty way to get what I wanted. I'll either get around to making it better later, or, well, the kids will have something a little more substantial than incorrect grammar corrections to do next Hacktoberfest.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Leaving Note-Taking Applications</title>
<link>https://ronitray.xyz/posts/notes-workflow.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020</pubDate>
<description>In which I attempt to simplify the way I take notes.</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the books I'm reading this week, <em>Make Time: How to Focus on what Matters Every Day</em> by Jake Knapp and John Zeratsky, which is, by the way, the least self-helpy self-help book I've read in a while, maybe ever, had this passage that really resonated with me:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I’ve been burned by fancy tools. Back in 2006, I discovered the perfect productivity software: a simple but powerful app called Mori that allowed for infinitely customizable note taking and filing. I was elated, and spent countless hours configuring Mori on my laptop and loading all my projects into it. And I was right: It was perfect. Mori became an extension of my brain.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>But after a few months, things started breaking down. I upgraded my computer’s operating system, only to find that Mori wasn’t compatible with the new version. I’d want to look at my notes at home but realize I had left my laptop at work. And then the developer shut down Mori altogether. I was distraught.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>That’s the other problem with fancy tools: they’re fragile. Anything from a technical glitch to my own forgetfulness could keep me from getting into Laser mode and spending time on my Highlight. After Mori vanished, I started using simple, readily available tools to manage my work: text files on my computer, notes on my phone, basic Post-its, free hotel pens, that sort of thing. More than ten years later, my everyday tools work as well as ever. And whenever I get tempted by a new fancy tool, I just remember Mori.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now I've never used Mori, but as I have been getting acquainted with the online productivity/self-improvement scene over the last few months, there has been a lot of talk about note-taking tools, workflows, and techniques. I've been drawn to it partly out of an appreciation for new technology as well as a desire to integrate note-taking into my life with some level of seriousness.</p>

<p>I'd like to think I value privacy more than most other things, and try to consider the privacy-convenience tradeoff for everything I do or adopt. So my findings about existing note-taking platforms were a little underwhelming: </p>

<ul>
<li><a href="www.evernote.com">Evernote</a> is encrypted "in-transit", which is a nice to-have, but not really useful against anything other than MITM attacks. My understanding is my notes would be stored in plaintext or some kind of basic encoding on their servers, that is fully accessible and decryptable by them. I can encrypt individual notes but there's no way I'd do it manually for every single note. It's not convenient.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.onenote.com/">OneNote</a> claims to be encrypted at rest, which is not bad, but the keys are still generated, owned and controlled by Microsoft. I'd be trusting them with my data.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.notion.so/">Notion</a> doesn't even bother to talk of encryption, their privacy policy is a little invasive-sounding to my paranoid brain, and essentially boils down to <em>trust us</em>, which I suppose is fair for this kind of service but I have no reason to trust them, any more than Microsoft for example.</li>
<li><a href="https://standardnotes.org/">Standard Notes</a> is end-to-end encrypted and really awesome, I stuck with it for the longest time but it doesn't support Markdown on the free tier and the premium tier is a little expensive for my working-class Indian wallet that only started earning last year.</li>
<li><a href="https://joplinapp.org/">Joplin</a> is very usable and was finally what I landed upon. Markdown is really easy to use, and it supported E2EE, with the caveat that I had to use another cloud storage service like Dropbox/OneDrive to store the encrypted notes on the cloud. Which means I am trusting at least two parties (Joplin and the cloud storage provider) to handle my data safely and really stay afloat.</li>
</ul>

<p>This comes down to the passage from <em>Make Time.</em> I was already using Markdown in Joplin, and exporting my notes to a folder structure was trivial. I figured there's really no reason for my workflow to have to rely on either Joplin or a cloud provider for sync. Here's what I did:</p>

<ol>
<li>"Notebooks" and nested notebooks/sections are just simple folders in a directory structure. Zero restrictions and it makes sense everywhere.</li>
<li>Notes are markdown files that are readable as-is as well as convertable to a prettier form, supporting web formatting for things like lists, tables, code snippets and blockquotes which I needed.</li>
<li>Full text search with grep is the easiest thing ever. </li>
<li>I edit notes in Vim, my text editor of choice on Linux desktop. There's no reason I wouldn't be able to edit them in any other editor, because they're text files.</li>
<li>I also use the <a href="https://github.com/JamshedVesuna/vim-markdown-preview">vim-markdown-preview add-on</a> because it's very minimal, and doesn't need me to install NodeJS or some other bloated framework. Sure, no live preview, but rendering the note in a browser window beside the editor takes milliseconds and is just a hotkey away at any point in time.</li>
<li>I use <a href="https://syncthing.net/">Syncthing</a> to locally sync my entire notes folder with my Android phone. It uses my local network so my files never travel over the internet (you can literally disconnect your ethernet cable to be sure). It is very easy to use once set up, and since the files themselves are really light (again, text files, woo-freaking-hoo!) sync is a matter of seconds even at scale.</li>
<li>On my android phone, my notes viewer/editor of choice is the very powerful and versatile open-source <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.gsantner.markor&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US">Markor</a>, which has no internet permissions (and I've blocked from accessing the internet anyway via a firewall, just in case) and offers a great Markdown viewer as well as WYSIWYG editor if I need to write notes on the phone.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is pretty much everything I needed, brought down to established open-source components and standards where possible. It is widely compatible, very portable, and easy enough to replace any one component if I need to, which is great. I'll figure out a redundancy solution eventually, but I reckon it's just a matter of setting up a backup script on a crontab or adding the notes folder to an rsync/Timeshift backup if I so desire.</p>

<p>I'm going to slug it out with this setup for a while at least, and see if it fits the bill. There might be parts of it I revisit in the future to improve usability/convenience/security, but time will tell. For now, I'm happy. Which is rare these days.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>